Guide to the Martin Packard papers
Stanford University Libraries.
- 6. Varian miscellaneous business files
  - Instrument Group Strategic Plan, 1981-1985 (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - project discussion forms (Box 54, Folder 7)
  - Profit Impact of Marketing Strategy (Marketing Science Institute) (1) (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Profit Impact of Marketing Strategy (Marketing Science Institute) (2) (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Meetings With ELG, 1982-1989 (Box 55, Folder 3)
    Edward Ginzton, who was part of the company from its inception, was Varian’s Chairman of the Board following Russell’s death in 1959. As Assistant to Board Chairman, Packard met with him regularly, and they continued to meet following Ginzton's retirement in 1984. These agendas, largely concerning Varian business in the USSR and China, are annotated by Packard. There are also related agendas in the Varian history series.
  - Cassette Files [ROI forecasts on computer printouts], 1972-1974 (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Expense Reports, 1967-1979 (Box 55, Folder 5)
  - Expense Reports, 1980-1989 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Map (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - X-Ray Tube Failure Analysis [computer printout], 1980 (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - Schedule for Visit of USSR Delegation [computer printout], 1977-03-17 (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - Castle Rock (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - Magazine list (MEP to Library), 1978 (Box 56, Folder 6)
  - Chinese scientists at Varian, 1987 (Box 56, Folder 7)
    Correspondence and documents related to two Chinese scientists (Lu Guo and Lin Bin Sheng of Dalian) working and studying in the United States, as well as negotations for a trip to China by Packard.
  - Varian - 25 Years [pamphlet] (Box 56, Folder 8)
  - Your Future With Varian [pamphlet] (Box 56, Folder 9)
- 7. Palo Alto Capital Company, 1967-1975
  In the late 1960s, Varian Associates, and Edward Ginzton in particular, had an interest in assisting “members of minorities to establish and expand successful small business in the mid-Peninsula area,” and founded a Minority Enterprise Small Business Investment Company (MESBIC) to that end. Varian’s Minority Employment Committee worked with the Stanford-Mid-Peninsula Urban Coalition in setting up an SBIC that would also coordinate volunteer business consultation and management development, in addition to providing loans. The Palo Alto Capital Company, founded in October 1969, was the second MESBIC in country. PACC merged with Opportunity Capital Corporation of San Francisco in 1974, with Martin Packard representing Varian on their Board of Directors.
  - MESBICs, ELG, 1969-1970 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - American Association of MESBICS Annual Conference - Position Papers, 1975-10 (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Minority Employment Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 65, Folder 3)
  - Palo Alto Capital Company, 1969-1975 (Box 65, Folder 4)
  - Palo Alto Capital Company. Schedule "A," Arcata (Box 65, Folder 5)
- 8. Other organizations
  - 8.1. Addiction Research Foundation (ARF), 1974-1989
    The Addiction Research Foundation was a nonprofit research clinic devoted to the study of addictive diseases, formed by Avram Goldstein, a professor of pharmacology at Stanford University School of Medicine who advocated for the recognition of addiction as a behavioral disorder. Goldstein was one of the discoverers of endorphins, in part because of the work he was able to accomplish at the Foundation. Goldstein was a consultant to Varian-related company Syva prior to the Addiction Research Foundation, and Packard was on the ARF Board of Directors from the beginning. Varian also sold the group some analytical instruments. The Foundation originally offered experimental treatment of heroin addicts, and later studied nicotine addiction and the development of non-addictive pain-killers. The collection only contains organizational records, and no medical or scientific data is present.
    - General 1970s (Box 61, Folder 8)
    - Organization and Policies, 1974-1977 (Box 62, Folder 5)
    - Fundraising, 1977-1985 (Box 61, Folder 4)
    - Executive Committee, 1979 (Box 61, Folder 5)
    - Stanford Affiliation, 1976-1986 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Loan Guaranty Proposal, 1979 (Box 61, Folder 7)
    - General, 1980-1984 (Box 62, Folder 4)
    - Litigation, 1980 (Box 62, Folder 6)
    - Patents, 1984-1985 (Box 62, Folder 2)
    - General, 1985-1986 (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors, 1985-1987 (Box 62, Folder 3)
    - Symposium, 1987-1988 (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - Closing (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - Trust, 1987-1988 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - 8.2. Panel on Scientific Communication and National Security (National Academy of Sciences), 1982
    - Draft Report, 1982-08-18 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    - Draft Report, 1982-09-07 (Box 66, Folder 2)
    - Appendices, 1982-09-07 (Box 66, Folder 3)
    - Working Papers (Box 66, Folder 4)
    - misc. articles and papers (Box 66, Folder 5)
    - meeting materials [papers, memos, draft documents], 1982-07 (Box 62, Folder 6)
  - 8.3. Panel on the Impact of National Security Controls on International Technology Transfer (National Academies of Sciences and Engineering Committee on Science, Engineering and Public Policy), 1986
    - 4th and 5th Meeting Summaries, 1986 (Box 65, Folder 6)
    - misc. documents, 1985-1986 (Box 65, Folder 7)
    - Does the Russian Ethos Affect Technological Information Transfer? (MEP) (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - working papers, 1986-03 (Box 65, Folder 9)
    - working papers, 1986-04 (Box 67, Folder 1)
    - Analysis of the Effects of U.S. National Security Controls on U.S.-Headquartered Industrial Firms, 1986-07-10 (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - 8.4. Vega Biotechnologies, 1982-1985
    Packard was on the Board of Directors for this Arizona-based company which had connections to Varian.
    - Prospectus (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Form 10-K and Proxy Statement (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors (Box 63, Folder 3)
    - Vega (1) (Box 63, Folder 4)
- 9. Instrument brochures
  - Varian product brochures (Box 56, Folder 10)
  - Varian brochures - Spectrometers, NMR (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - Varian brochures - Chromatographs (Box 57, Folder 2)
  - Instrument Study Brochures (Non-Varian) (Box 57, Folder 3)
- 10. Articles and papers, 1981-1982
  - scientific instrument articles, advertisements [clippings and photocopies] (Box 63, Folder 8)
  - articles, papers, other publications (Box 64, Folder 1)
- 11. Packard papers, presentations, etc.
  - miscellaneous speeches, papers (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Instruments as Peripherals (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - Packard/Rempel - Rubidium Vapor Frequency Standards, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - Free Nuclear Precession Magnetomter, 1956 (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - Publications, 1946-1962 (Box 60, Folder 5)
  - Good RF and Microwave Practices at Varian, 1982-01-18 (Box 60, Folder 6)
  - Good RF transparencies (Box 60, Folder 7)
  - A Study of The Future of NMR At Vartian, 1981-10-01 (Box 60, Folder 8)
  - Transfer of Technological Information, 1982-05-25 (Box 60, Folder 9)
  - Deposition. Sinclair Oil Corporation vs. Union Oil Company / Hiroca Corporation vs. Union Oil Company, 1969-01-09 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Deposition. Perkin-Elmer Corporation vs. Varian Associates, Inc., 1985-09-11 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - William Hodge (personal), 1972-1984 (Box 63, Folder 7)
- 12. Notebooks, calendar planners, business cards
  - Planners, 1956, 1961, 1962 (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - Planners, 1975-1980 (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - Planners, 1981-1984 (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - Planners, 1985-1988 (Box 58, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks (Box 58, Folder 3)
  - Notebooks, 1960-1964 (Box 58, Folder 4)
  - Notebooks, Business Cards (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - Notebooks [travel and business], 1972, 1978-1986 (Box 59, Folder 2)
- 13. Audiovisual material, [2 videocasettes; 1 audiocassette; one photograph]
  - A Valley Changes The World. H.P. Born. Swiss Radio. Fall, 1983; 1 audiocassette(s) BASF LH super I. 120 minute (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - Dr. Bloch. M. Packard, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) Scotch T-120 (Box 67, Folder 4)
  - Varian Associates. Video Marketing Program. Circa, 1985; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) dub (Box 67, Folder 5)
  - Chemical Show, Beijing. Lu Peichang, 1988-10; 1 photoprint(s) (Box 67, Folder 6)
- 14. Tubes and other machine parts, 6 Item(s)
  Vacuum tubes from Varian and Westinghouse (although Packard worked at the latter, these tubes may date from after his time there), as well as a possible vacuum cavity from Westinghouse and other unidentified tubes or parts.
  - [unidentified] (Box 68)
    no markings, approx. 1.5" long. red band, striated glass or plastic. plug on one end. in tiny box labeled "delicate handle with care"
  - [unidentified] (Box 68)
    no markings except "licensed only to extent indicated on carton." 5" long, octal (introduced 1935). all black. partly connected by springs and screws. nozzle on side. possibly a prototype
  - Westinghouse 1B24 (Box 68)
    D85223 [stamped]]; [anchor stamp]. [on envelope: RBC; LF3895; B56A6; 1648]
  - Westinghouse WL-1Q22 [vacuum cavity] (Box 68)
    US [anchor stamp]. 113,337 [stamped]; 109039 [engraved] "X-band, fixed frequency vacuum cavity: 9250MHz resonating frequency, 1900 to 2400 unloaded Q. Flanged waveguide connections. Used to stabilize the frequency of the klystron local oscillator in radar receivers."
  - Varian JAN-1B24A tube [top part, glass] (Box 68)
    Co60. 7232
  - Varian JAN-1B24A tube [bottom part, metal] (Box 68)